[SPEAKER_00]: I have a question specifically on one passage, but I figure I'll just go through the whole thing, because David might come up with that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, if I heard, on one occasion, the Blessed One was dwelling at Rādhika in the hot spring park, and the Venerable Samādhi, having risen at the first flush of dawn, went to the hot springs to bathe, having bathed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, when the night advanced, certain Devata approached Him, having approached, she stood in the air and addressed the Venerable Samādhi in verse.
Without having enjoyed, you seek alms, bhikkhu.
You don't seek alms after you've enjoyed.
First enjoy, bhikkhu, then seek alms.
Don't let the time pass you by.
He responds, I do not know what the time might be.
The time is hidden and cannot be seen.
Hence, without enjoying, I seek alms.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do not let the time pass me by.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was a common belief as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: You enjoy sensuality until you get old.
Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when you can't get as much from it, then you go full.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even today, I can see that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's all on the assumption that you're going to live forever, or that you're going to at least reach an old age.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even that's not a guarantee.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what monk says.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I don't know the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: I might die tomorrow, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, to exchange, eh... she... the day that goes on.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have gone forth while young, a lad of black hair, endowed with the blessing of youth and the prime of life, without having dallied with sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_00]: Enjoy human sensual pleasures.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do not abandon what is directly visible, in order to pursue what takes time.
[SPEAKER_00]: He responds, I have not abandoned what is directly visible, in order to pursue what takes time.
[SPEAKER_00]: I have abandoned
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's kind of like saying that even like, you know, seeing the dhamma, practicing renunciation even, it just happens there, right now, instead of going out, finding it, going through all the work,
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it refers basically to dhamma being timeless.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Literally, it's visible directly, not involving time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, going forward into the ordaining and in the piety, alms round, whatever he's doing, that takes time, but that's not the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: The actual seeing of the dhamma, it's the most direct visible thing one can develop, which is why it can uproot everything else that does involve time.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it still takes, in a sense...
[SPEAKER_00]: Practice of dhamma takes time, but dhamma doesn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dhamma doesn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's all there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Simultaneously present, basically, for as long as your aggregates are present.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it doesn't pertain.
[SPEAKER_01]: It uproots the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't depend on them, like everything else that you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: That would involve time.
[SPEAKER_00]: How is the dhamma like that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Somebody says, I am newly ordained, not long gone forth.
[SPEAKER_00]: I cannot explain it in detail, but the Blessed One dwelling here, you can ask him about this matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: David says, lament, it isn't easy for us to approach the Blessed One as he is surrounded by others.
[SPEAKER_00]: David has a great influence.
Somebody says, okay, I'll go, I'll go ask and you come along with me.
[SPEAKER_00]: The day that I asked somebody to ask the Blessed One, I was writing that conversation, and the Blessed One says these two verses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Beings who perceive what can be expressed, become established in what can be expressed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not fully understanding what can be expressed, they come under the yoke of death.
[SPEAKER_00]: But having fully understood what can
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this, even a long time ago, struck me as a two verses, very kind of full of meaning.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it was only recently, when we got into discussing things like, you know, designations and stuff, that it kind of like, oh, it's kind of clicking, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's exactly what it refers to, as lethargy expressed.
[SPEAKER_01]: That which can be designated, you can just hope that it says the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, the extent of the name in regard to the matter, which is the extent of the all.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the issue is not perceiving what can be expressed.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's going to be everyone, but it's becoming established.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Assuming.
[SPEAKER_01]: Developing assumptions upon that which is expressed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether it's like the different types of conceivings in and out, apart from indifferent, the same, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the problem, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the name is never a problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: There never was.
[SPEAKER_01]: Never met.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not that the issue is not in there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, for example...
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes people try to deny the designation, try to deny the name, and then it may be... Well, I'm sure you've heard that in America.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've heard a lot of it in England from people among saying,
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Conventional truth and ultimate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, well, you can designate whichever you wanted.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a present experience and it's real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, conventional reality and, again, there is also quite a serious contradiction contained in that, but they're not worried.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you say, that's just conventional reality, as opposed to the ultimate reality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you just designated the ultimate reality in the same manner you designate the conventional reality, which means ultimate reality is also conventional reality.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you didn't name it in the same way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you named it, didn't you?
[SPEAKER_01]: How are you going to... Oh, it's inexpressible.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just expressed it by calling it inexpressible.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the ending way of relation will be relation through name and matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: It can't be any other way.
[SPEAKER_01]: But people, they want to replace name with something greater than the name that they're used to.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's greater only in relation to what they're used to.
[SPEAKER_01]: After a while, that won't be.
[SPEAKER_01]: That will be the conventional norm.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, the context I usually heard in most regretting self, like, you know, they'd say, oh, you know, we talk about myself, but it's just convention.
[SPEAKER_00]: The ultimate reality is there is no self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what your self is at the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's the deniable self.
[SPEAKER_00]: The tangle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it really is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's, yeah, very, very prevalent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Becoming established
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, bottom line, that can, you know, result in... well, in this use that we just discussed, you can deny, you can say that's secondary, you can say that's primary, you can say that's not real, you can say that's real.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of those things are... when you refer to that name, to that which can be expressed apart from yourself, basically, you leave yourself excluded, you become the center of the expression.
[SPEAKER_01]: You become defined by it, by sort of placing the attitude of assumption upon it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether like this or like that, both or neither, doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: What matters is yourself is assumed separate from it, independent of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's fundamentally what assumption means and why it's a problem and why it allows for self-view to be filled.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because an assumption like that is such that ignores
One's self, so to say.
Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, for example, the one I thought about a lot is burning, uh, you know, matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: I would think of all, you know...
[SPEAKER_01]: It ignores, it ignores, not necessarily one's self, it ignores the ownership of one's self.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, as you just said, people can say, there is no self.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they can really think about it, not self, but they own that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, which means
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, conceiving, you can regard as subtler than assumption, but it's the same movement, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, conceivings result in assumptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: When there are assumptions, it means conceivings are there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, yeah, you can be free from course assumptions, just to have some conceivings of a subtler nature, but that's like anāgāmī, ārāhant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, worry about that later.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like with the
[SPEAKER_00]: That matter, that, for example, you know, we can have the assumption that, uh, oh, the thought I have of matter is that actual matter.
That's an assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: I guess what's not very clear to me is, okay, I can make that assumption, but how, how is that connected to my view of myself?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, by, see, by conceiving the matter in such manner, by giving it a being,
[SPEAKER_01]: You became the owner of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: By giving it a being.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you're responsible for bhāva.
[SPEAKER_01]: Matter is.
[SPEAKER_01]: By you thinking that thought is what the matter is, means that thought that you have, that you think the matter is, is what matter is, in your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have the real reference to real matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, well, I don't want to say real matter as opposed to that sound matter, but that's real.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your assumption is real.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your assumption is real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's what... it's how matter exists at the time for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you give the being.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where matter finds footing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you give matter... being to the matter through the assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what... that's why the... Upādāna pāche bhāva, bhāva, direct result of your assumption is
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no, that's what matter is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you're thinking now, oh, there's my assumption matter, and then there is real matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no real matter for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whenever you think matter, you assume matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only way to notice your matter is to stop conceiving.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, that experience would be the experience of, like, the five aggregates free from upādāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now, you still think that you have a clear thought of what matter is, but you fail to see that that thought stands for that which you think the matter is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you end up conceiving with a secondary thought, not with the first one.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, matter is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you can say that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means matter is assumed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there's not like no matter, either.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, again, that's the denial of the matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, again, that's also a negative form of being.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is no of this matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, like, for example, when we ever talk about... actually, I will come again and say the AI is the fleshy organ in the world by which
[SPEAKER_00]: There's vision.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when I think of that I, it's never the I.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's always the thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: But now, see, when you say that, now you already imply with your peripheral thoughts that something else, another thought, is that I.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, no thought is the I.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: The I is I.
[SPEAKER_01]: The thought is thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can have a thought of the I, you can designate whichever you want, as long as that thought does not imply the conceiving of the I.
[SPEAKER_01]: The I does not find a footing in that thought as it's existing there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Clearing these domains from confusion, from the assumptions of overlap, the assumptions of mixing, the assumptions of finding footing in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to deny or affirm anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just have to think your thoughts, feel your feelings, and perceive your perceptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: And these three are separate things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Simultaneously present always, but not the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: And certainly cannot be mixed or interfere with each other.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I can think about
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what you are getting the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: I wish there was vision all I want, but it's never the I.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Never will be, can't be.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even when you make a statement that it's never the I, never will be, make sure that that statement, then, does not imply, through the peripheral background, some other less defined thought that's assumed to be that real I.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's just a matter of
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you end up only being able to only know that you're only going to think your thoughts, nothing else, but that's possible because the real matter, the matter in itself, it's present there.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when you have clarity of these thoughts, then the thought that matter that's present there, because of which I'm able to think about matter or anything else, you won't be conceiving, because you reach the clarity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you see that they're entirely separate domains.
[SPEAKER_01]: You will have enough of the mindfulness span, so to speak, that no peripheral background can induce more confusion, because the matter is clear to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Literally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pun intended there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the point is, when you, when, as I said, when you make a statement and you're going to thought like, oh, well, this is not that which matter is, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the mind hasn't been developed to, to kind of not lose the span, so to speak, which means that without a sufficient span, you're going to assume that some other thought is then the real matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when you know that the matter is there, and that thought doesn't stand for that, because of which that thought, that matter is there, is there, then you're fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you don't have to go further.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nobody has to stop short.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this kind of thing's... That's completely unraveling of your thinking, in a sense of freeing it from any assumptions and concealings.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's developed by the repetition.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thinking that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's still, I think, correct me if I'm wrong, a good direction to say,
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, my thought of the I is not the I, but then I also have to take it as far as it needs to go as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah, absolutely.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not saying that's the wrong thing to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm just saying you have to keep taking it further.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because often people would say that, and then, okay, that's clear.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's clear only when it's unraveled.
[SPEAKER_00]: It might have to be where the infinity, the directional one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, when you make a statement, ah, this thought is not that, because of which the thought is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, this thought is not that matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, just... you don't even have to, kind of, go in a fully defined thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just need to remain mindful of the peripheral attitude of your mind, then, to, kind of, fall into something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: No matter how non-defined that else might is or might be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sounds like a very subtle thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just like a habit of mind to take this, to take that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you take this, then you... you recognize it, that this cannot be that.
[SPEAKER_01]: What you've taken it to be, what you took it to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, you just make sure, okay, now that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't overdo it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't, like, find something else, then, to not take.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let it persist for as long as you want to persist, as such thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: But this is not that, because of which matter is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you find your mind falling on something else.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you redo it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Redo it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point is, you do it and then leave it while it's being present as something that's done.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you just basically remain mindful.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not like, oh, just be mindful.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can be mindful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anybody can be mindful.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you need to set it up properly, have a right thought, right intention, and then be mindful while it lasts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It seems then, it's almost like, in a way, it could be described as being aware of multiple things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, in terms of, you know, you're on one hand aware of the need for there to be materiality, for there to be thoughts of senses, thoughts of forms, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: At the same time, recognizing that that
[SPEAKER_00]: View of yours, of the I, that, you know, fleshy, elemental, external, however you want to call it, thing, even that's still not your I.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to see the infinity of where that direction will go.
[SPEAKER_00]: It seems like a whole, like, multiple...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can say, that's still not my I.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you will find your mind automatically assuming something else is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what you need to discern as that peripheral assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not make it into another thing and say, no, that's also not my eye, because then your mind will peripherally assume something else is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, when I say peripheral, it means like a negative thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not, it doesn't, doesn't become a positive center of your attention.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you need to see it as such, as a negative thought, not to make it a positive center of attention, because then something else would be a negative thought in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's, that's what I mean, like to
[SPEAKER_01]: Set it up and then leave it for as long as it lasts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't kind of keep bringing it and making it positive, making it positive, because the actual negative thought in regard to that, it's always going to remain obscured.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, like, like trying to, trying to set up, set up like a balance or something, and then it sort of, it falls.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, oh, it stands a bit longer, stands a bit longer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Actually, this stands pretty well.
[SPEAKER_01]: I need something that won't stay.
[SPEAKER_01]: This stays.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything stays here.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, this will be tricky.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, say, you're trying to vote, and it falls.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, you set it up, and it... oops... lasted for a second, lasted for... and then it... and it stays, stays, stays, stays, and then it falls.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, it stays.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't interfere while it is staying.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you just keep making positive, like, going... assuming that only the positive thought is the thought you need to be thinking,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, that's the problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, basically, you'll never allow balance to set, because you will be doing this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Intentionally bring it down and put it back up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it actually wants to stay on its own, you'll pick it up and put it again.
[SPEAKER_01]: You pick it up and you put it... you pick it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pick it up, let it fall, then put it up, let it fall, then pick it up, and it stays.
[SPEAKER_01]: Stays a bit longer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, don't pick it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: For as long as it stays.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, when it falls, you do the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pick it up again,
[SPEAKER_01]: But not just, like, picking it up, picking it up, picking it up, because then you wouldn't even discern what a balance is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, same principle as when you're, like, just doing things you're mindful of, like, let's say, your body in a peripheral way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like an anchor, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're anchored in the background so that you can actually keep seeing things if it's in the balance and if it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, let me set it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, it's wobbly, wobbly, wobbly, but it's still considered upright and that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to interfere with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: You set up the thought.
[SPEAKER_01]: This thought can only be the thought, not that because of which this thought is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And your mind lapsed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do it again.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then it won't lapse so quickly every time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes it will stay.
[SPEAKER_01]: That thought that you just thought, as a thought, not as that because of which the thought is there, is still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just be mindful of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's already practice of proper meditation as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wait for the background.
[SPEAKER_01]: Look at it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Discern it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Still the same thing is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to wait for it to end.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just relax now.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still up.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you find in mind, oh, it's not up anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: So every
[SPEAKER_01]: Change, so to speak, is abrupt, as Aniruddha was saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you won't find the moment when he kind of... it's not set up anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just want to find it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why most people have absolutely no sense of... a recognition of the notion of enduring, persisting while changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's where the mind development is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because arising is persisting while changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is increasing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ceasing is persisting while changing is decreasing, which means all you're going to have is different directions of enduring of things arising and ceasing in regard to your thoughts and feelings and perceptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the point is to train your mind in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if the balance is there, then you don't have to interfere.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not knowing what the balance is, you'll just keep doing everything and nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you certainly wouldn't know how to set it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, oh, he can obtain first jhānas at will.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because he fully understood them.
[SPEAKER_00]: He can just think it and he answers it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's hard for me to wrap my head around the idea of both, like, a positive and negative thought at the same time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's so easy to visualize.
[SPEAKER_01]: It takes training.
[SPEAKER_01]: It takes repetition.
[SPEAKER_01]: Training of the mind to start discerning it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't visualize the negative, because you're visualizing positive, which means that has something else as negative in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, while you're visualizing, you start discerning the background of that visualization, of that thought, without making it then the central, because then something else would be the periphery.
[SPEAKER_00]: If we use this example in terms of consciousness,
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's say, you know, okay, there are things, name and form.
[SPEAKER_00]: One can't even really make consciousness positive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the ultimate negative.
[SPEAKER_01]: One makes consciousness positive through basically appropriating it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how consciousness gets established, as it says in the sutras.
[SPEAKER_01]: But actually, in its nature, yeah, consciousness is the ultimate.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, for an arahant,
[SPEAKER_01]: What's that translation?
[SPEAKER_01]: The non-indicative consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically means consciousness that doesn't point to anything anymore, which means that consciousness is inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's, you know, the mind is liberated.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't set, doesn't get established upon anything that has appeared.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anything, however big or small, is just left for what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there's still like awareness of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, but even that awareness belongs to those things, those phenomena that has arisen, not to your end of the stick, which there isn't, your end of the stick.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is, well, there is a sense of self, center of me, but when that's abandoned, then there isn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in terms of, like, establishing mindfulness in that kind of direction, so, like,
You know, things appear.
I can be aware of that.
Are they positive things, sights, sounds, whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: But in the, I guess you could say, back of my mind, somehow not making it a positive thought of consciousness, the mind can be trained to be aware that these things are only there because there is a... What do you mean not making it a positive thought of consciousness?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if I'm looking at a thing and I'm saying...
[SPEAKER_00]: I make a positive thought saying, oh, I can only see these because there is consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like making it a thought and then assuming the thought is the consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can still, in a sense, know that there can only be things because there is consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can discern.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can know what consciousness is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then that... That's why the suttas, it says that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Consciousness is to be fully understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's identifying consciousness within your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: Consciousness is where understanding is.
[SPEAKER_01]: The consciousness that has been liberated from many assumptions and concealings, in the same sense the matter that has been liberated from concealing, is the nature or the experience of understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in everything that appears understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: The nature of things is understood, the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you're still obviously trying to explain it to yourself, which is fine, but you make sure you don't settle on the explanation.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point is, when I said you have to develop your mind in regard to the phenomenon of things enduring as they have arisen,
[SPEAKER_01]: That means, basically, the center of the experience, of your experience, is not in you, or on you, or with you, or yours.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically in that which is enduring at the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever attention, whatever that thing might be, whether it's a thought, feeling, or perception, as that upon which your attention is set up and you're mindful of, that is the center of your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: From there, you infer, subtly, implicitly, sense of self and sense of ownership and everything, but only because thing has arisen first, beforehand, you find it there.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the center of the experience, basically, slowly shifts onto the actual arising and ceasing.
[SPEAKER_01]: The five aggregates, the nature is to rise, having arisen, the nature is to cease.
[SPEAKER_01]: But both arising is manifest, cessation is manifest.
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you mean by the center shifts to the...
[SPEAKER_01]: The center from your sense of self shifts on to the center of arising of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because now it's me and things that are around me and they're happening to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that center me exists only because you own things that happen to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means it's not a center.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's dependent.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's actually... it's dependent upon
[SPEAKER_01]: Ownership of things that arise... My self is not a center.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just layered over things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Plastered over.
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you mean, plastered over?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, for example... Well, your self that feels like a center, myself, my center self, right here.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is... it's real as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you want to see that that's a mistake.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to uproot it by seeing that this very center of self, the real center of self,
[SPEAKER_01]: Depends upon ownership of these things that are not my center, that cannot be my center.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, my center depends upon that, which means folk.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's not really...
[SPEAKER_01]: When I say the center, the center implies the mind, you know, the puppeteer, the string puller, the one who controls all of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you're saying center, you're saying control?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what sense of self is.
[SPEAKER_01]: The center of the experience, the main hub.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was getting confused in terms, like, the mind being
[SPEAKER_01]: Right, right, right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that could correspond, which is why people assume myself is my mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Similar, but that's a different thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm talking about the actual, just sense of center, that the sense of self implies.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right here, as opposed to everywhere else.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's everywhere else.
[SPEAKER_01]: The experience as a whole, that has to arise first, and endure as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: From, like, and through, like, a constant ignorant habits and assumptions, you develop, you assume this center here, to which things happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: With the understanding that the arisen things are more fundamental.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Structurally precede the center.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not temporarily.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's while the center is here, present, you have to see it, while it's there, as dependent upon that, which cannot be that center.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, even that ceases to be that master center.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, with regards to arising and ceasing, it's... one's seeing that in terms of like... like things arise, cease, you know, become more present, less present indoors.
I don't know where you're going with that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, it's not... You can't, you can't, you can, you can explain it to yourself, you can get the intellectual idea of it, but it won't make you understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, like, that's true for everything, but with this particularly, that's why nobody understands it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why people even, often, they don't even say arising, ceasing, persisting, or changing.
[SPEAKER_01]: They say arising, enduring, ceasing.
[SPEAKER_01]: They change the order because the thing doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: It absolutely matters.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you say arising, enduring, ceasing, I mean, no, you're just witnessing things arising and then persisting for a while and then disappearing externally.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you leave yourself entirely out.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you also fail to see that whether it's arising, whether it's ceasing, that in itself is manifest.
[SPEAKER_01]: That in itself is already arising, like cessation.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's manifested in your experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means it has arisen as such, as cessation.
[SPEAKER_01]: How else are you going to know it?
[SPEAKER_01]: If you... if you actually... understanding of your experience means understanding of impermanence, which means understanding of the actual cessation of things, as if, in a sense, when you look at... look at a...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: I understand that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you don't watch things get destroyed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can't... you can't do that to yourself, man.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, I haven't.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be impossible while you're alive.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, what you're basically...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you... and you don't... you don't have to also look for where is the arising, where is the arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's always something there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like even now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You already have thoughts, feelings, moods, perceptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, take a pick.
[SPEAKER_01]: Plenty of things to establish your mindfulness upon and to discern that they're enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can say the five aggregates are enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: Each of them, independent of each other, are simultaneously enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: The form is enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: The feelings are enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: The perceptions are enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: The determinations are enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the consciousness is enduring.
[SPEAKER_01]: Five domains.
[SPEAKER_01]: Five heaps.
[SPEAKER_01]: Simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Act.
[SPEAKER_01]: But heaps.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't blend into one mush.
[SPEAKER_01]: They remain independent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Heaps.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it's heaps.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in regards to those, you know, you can see them persisting.
[SPEAKER_00]: How is it that
[SPEAKER_00]: One can discern them as arising.
[SPEAKER_01]: Are they increasing in their persistence, or are they decreasing in their persistence?
[SPEAKER_00]: They're arising, or they're ceasing?
[SPEAKER_00]: Increasing in persistence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is the endurance, is it like fading in?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it increasing in its presence, or is it decreasing its presence?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you say that in a matter of attending to it, or is that a different thing entirely?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you find it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, say you pick a feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that feeling, is it... okay, it's present.
[SPEAKER_01]: No doubt about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, is it increasing?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it going to be more of the same feeling?
[SPEAKER_01]: Or is it kind of fading out?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's still the same feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Still has the identity of the same feeling.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, is it increasing or is it decreasing in its presence?
[SPEAKER_00]: Some say the strength of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: The intensity of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where you're referring to particular things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I refer to this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well,
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't pick particular things and do that, because I'll be myself doing this thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You find that in your experience already, which means you always have to start with the experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: That becomes the particular thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is there an all this within that field?
[SPEAKER_01]: With... yeah, I suppose, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: On the basis of that field.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, first, you have to basically learn how to be mindful of the experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing specific.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just experience as a whole of me sitting in the room, on the chair, holding a book.
[SPEAKER_00]: Isn't that specific?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, as such, but it's not as specific as if you were to just be mindful of you holding a book.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like intensely focusing on my holding a book?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or don't, like, look for things out there to do the practice I'm just describing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's when you start with experience as a whole, and then within that, particular things might emerge.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even if they don't, that can then be your particular thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: The non-emergence of anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just in this room.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is enduring, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: And in the same, on the same level, so to speak, you will find feelings as moods, as like mind shapes, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Expanded, depressed, elated, light, heavy, high, full of energy.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of those are basically states of your mind that you discern as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not you who is depressed or you who is elated.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just the mind is elated.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind is depressed.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind is neither.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, the mind is invisible.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, the mind is very visible.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can designate whichever you want.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you start discerning the mind like that, it will stand for that which your mind is, who you're discerning.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then it's enduring as such.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it can be going throughout your day, but the mind is still in this depressed mood.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you see, again, when you re-attend the same depressed mood, then you find it's weakening, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, so you're not doing anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just the mind, the mood of the mind, is fading out.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's ceasing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's occurring without anything on your part.
[SPEAKER_00]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, oh, next thing you know, you get distracted, then you re-attend your mind where it was, and then
[SPEAKER_01]: It's actually quite peaceful, my mind, now.
[SPEAKER_01]: That has... oh, is this peace now coming over?
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a new thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's increasing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can do that with anything?
[SPEAKER_01]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you want to do it with mind, with feelings.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because those things are the ones that matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if you do it on that level, it means the mind is sufficiently developed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, obviously, yeah, you can do it with anything you intend to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Find it either increasing or decreasing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, I don't want to only do all this with right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, but in order to try to do it rightly, you can get the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Grasping the sign of the mind is a prerequisite for the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly what it means.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't see your mind in any state if you have absolutely no sign of the phenomenon of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not even a remote nimitta of, like, the shape of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you start discerning that, okay, there you go.
[SPEAKER_00]: Are we getting into a kind of a different approach here from senses, so to say?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I wouldn't worry about the approach of senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you can use anything for your practicing of your reflection.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, no matter what approach you're coming to, it has to start on the basis of mindfulness of the experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what's in common to anything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, because that is a starting point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, say, say things have proliferated mistakenly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to bring it back to the point that's kind of good enough, close to the point when it doesn't matter what proliferation is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that point is experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, if you start even picking writing based upon the right instruction, or I'll attend to this, I'll attend to this, but you attend it further down the line, after things have proliferated,
[SPEAKER_01]: It won't work then.
[SPEAKER_01]: It won't take the root.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but I'm saying, like, attendant means exactly what I said before.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to start with experience as a whole, not just pick an object within already a non-mindful experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you discern the object within the experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't pick the object on top of the experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a different direction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Can you say that again?
[SPEAKER_01]: You discern the object within the experience as a whole that you're mindful of.
[SPEAKER_01]: Within that, then, you discern the object without losing the mindfulness of the experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the opposite direction from the direction of how to pick an object, without a basis of experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't pick it, you find it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You step into it, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's two of those two simultaneous things, a particular general positive, negative one, say?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but the order does matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, you know, you...
[SPEAKER_01]: I can have a...
[SPEAKER_01]: I can... like, there you go.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can be...
[SPEAKER_01]: I can be attending to this table and the things on the table.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's a particular thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, within that, I can be attending on the cup that's on top of the table.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now, the cup is more particular than the other particular thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, really, they're all particular things, because I'm forgetting about myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yourself and your situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why that proliferation methods.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to find a place
[SPEAKER_01]: Bring it back where you include yourself, which is experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's the proliferation that takes that sense of self out, and then leaves it, uh, leaves it intact, no matter what reflection you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, this cup is impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: This cup is mine.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's very dear to me, and so on and so forth.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's made of this.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's made of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You left yourself out again.
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you find yourself in experience as a whole, sitting in this room, thinking about this cup, that's very dear and precious gift that was given to me, which it
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, okay, so you start with yourself as the basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: And within that, you discern the object of their value.
[SPEAKER_01]: And in that direction, reflection can go.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not just go out, forgetting about yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where experience as a whole, mindfulness of it, needs to come first.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when we say a situation, it's...
[SPEAKER_01]: It implies you, always.
[SPEAKER_01]: It should.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you are always in the situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that can be anything as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, whatever you are, whatever you're doing, whatever you're thinking, whatever you're feeling, that's part of the experience as a whole that's already there.
[SPEAKER_01]: The presence of the five aggregates, that's the situation.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's also not a matter of saying, oh, this is the feeling that the perception... No, no, it doesn't matter, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can discern that within that situation, then.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you would actually be discerning that which feeling is.
[SPEAKER_01]: As opposed to just assuming and thinking, then attending upon your assumption of what you think the feeling is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's I mean, you find those things in the experience, once experience as a whole has been brought up, brought up to light with mindfulness sufficient amount of times.
[SPEAKER_01]: But without that as a basis, you're not actually fishing in the right pond, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, as you think of the words experience as a whole and situation, but I... there have only been maybe a few times where I've sort of been like, oh, this might actually be what that means.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, it's always kind of a vague thing, what that might mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it is, it is a vague, it will be a vague experience, because it's basically like mind waking up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mindful being constantly absorbed in things, just waking up.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why some people, that's why people, like, you know, they come across it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even people with the wrong view, just experience the whole mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the minds are blown away by it, because they're never used to it, that they spiritualize it, they mystify it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you can see that often, hear that certainly, and it's kind of the pinnacle of every teaching in every religion.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just be here now, be mindful, the pure presence, the pristine awareness.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just mystified mindfulness of the experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that in itself means nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: As you can see by all the different teachers and people that talk lots of stuff, that doesn't actually lead anywhere.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anybody can be mindful.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why I say, like, you need to know what you're supposed to look for.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, absolutely, mindfulness comes first.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can never have too much mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that in itself, it's certainly not the end.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's just the beginning.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for most people, that's where the practice ends.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just spend your rest of your life, just be here now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Mind, whatever, judgment-free, your mind is present, pristine awareness, all those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then what?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it'll work out eventually.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: By itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it won't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it doesn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you just end up revolving around more sophisticated wrong views.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or not even so sophisticated.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point is, mindfulness is not the end.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the beginning of your practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, start with that pristine awareness, which is a contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Call it whatever you want.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, within that, start discerning what you're supposed to know, which is what the suttas tell you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But don't use the sutra just to come to that experience and then mystify yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the feelings need to be understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: The thoughts need to be understood.
[SPEAKER_01]: The perception needs to be understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: How are you going to understand that if you just sort of... You don't see what's surrounding you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're just kind of frozen in this ecstatic... not even ecstatic, just this...
[SPEAKER_01]: Neither here nor there, all around, luminous presence of my pristine awareness, and then what?
[SPEAKER_01]: Great.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you actually don't forget that you're supposed to understand these things, then it becomes just wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: This is just mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindfulness of the experience itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure, feels light, feels luminous, feels whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the comparison to, like, states before, states of non-mindfulness, and when I said people are not mindful as if already dead,
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all true.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's what mindfulness is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you kind of wake up to do the work.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not wake up and celebrate that you woke up and you haven't done any work.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is what most spiritual practices are today.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just grateful, gratitude, ease and whatnot.
[SPEAKER_01]: But no work done.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just we reach this.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, look, we can be mindful.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, no wonder now people try to take the mindfulness and apply it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, speaking with a psychiatrist the other day in Kenya, Australia, and they were saying there's a whole movement, and I know there was even in England, this whole movement of applying mindfulness, like, not, not, not in a, not in a, like, a religious context, not in a Buddhist context, just, just the mindfulness for this mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just, yeah, great.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even the NHS in England, National Health, National Health Service, even they started doing courses in mindfulness therapy.
[SPEAKER_01]: Bless them.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, sure, mindfulness is always better than non-mindfulness, but don't mistake mere mindfulness for understanding of the dhamma and being free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's basically my point.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's on the stage, great.
[SPEAKER_01]: That often is, obviously.
[SPEAKER_01]: And people think it's the goal.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the goal of the whole practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just be here now, present.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are already now present, whether you want to be or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't have to make any effort to be present, because you have no choice about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you can just become aware of it, and then you can either go all mystical, or you can become aware of it, and as soon as, okay, now I have to do the work, because now I'm aware.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you do the work, and the work is understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Investigating the meaning, not leaving anything unturned, as many ways as the Buddha would put it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when it's understood, then, yeah, you can't help but not be mindful, obviously.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think an important criteria for myself is recognizing if a thought I'm having is a description versus an explanation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you know what I mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And see, that can also be determined whether you're mindful of it or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're mindful of it properly, it means you're not losing the base of the experience as a whole, which means then it's a description.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you can have the same thought, but it's baseless, and then it's an explanation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when we say explanation, that basically means almost like abstract.
[SPEAKER_01]: Becomes abstract, becomes abstracted from the base that's non-existent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Base being... Mindfulness as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I was saying, I think, in one of the talks with Tanya.
[SPEAKER_01]: I was telling that abstract is basically your attitude, not necessarily the content.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can think something great as an explanation, but it's not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you were to re-establish the mindfulness and have the same abstract thought, it will cease to be abstract, because now it's actually standing for that which it represents.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why I say, when Bhikkhu Bodhi, he says in his translations, oh, Paticca Upādāna, when this, this is, the first line, it's just an abstract principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then he goes on explaining rest of Paticca Upādāna differently.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, well, it's an abstract principle only because you don't understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, it's abstracted.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, far from dismissing something because it's abstract, that you just tell you that actually you don't understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you should understand it when it ceases to be abstract.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you read all this, when the Buddha describes the states of mind and whatever else, the people usually, oh, this is just abstract or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's abstract because you have no clue what he's talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have to find out and then it won't be abstract.
[SPEAKER_01]: The element of earth, the casino of earth, the casino of this, the casino of that... For most people, it's just abstract.
[SPEAKER_01]: They have absolutely no idea what they're referred to.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that doesn't mean that the actual content is abstract.
[SPEAKER_01]: It just means their minds are so far abstracted from that, they have no concept of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when we're doing it properly, like in terms of descriptions, if we want to use that word, as opposed to explanations,
[SPEAKER_00]: It means, then, that we have that background, we have awareness of it, and then...
[SPEAKER_01]: Within that, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, of course, I can say that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's easy enough to say.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's easy enough to say, but it's hard to repeat it sufficient amount of times.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's not impossible.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's not hard in terms of
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, crap, how can I be mindful of the experiences?
[SPEAKER_01]: Everybody can be mindful of the experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing specific, just on the in and out.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can start with that if you want.
[SPEAKER_01]: Within that, then, without losing that, you have to develop discernment.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's just repetition.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by losing that, we get absorbed, it's absorption, like, wrongly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You lose it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Basically, it ceases to be the basis of your description, of your reflection, of your investigation, of your meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's basic.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It ceases to be that, which means you've fallen off the right base.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're not looking at the right place.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might be looking at the same thing, but from a completely wrong angle.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that angle is an angle that's not rooted, not established upon the right base.
[SPEAKER_01]: of mindfulness of the experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, you can say, I'm mindful of the experience as a whole, and you can know.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might not know that specifically, but you know, whatever the Buddha ever talked about in the suttas, however abstract or not, is to be found within this mindfulness of the experience as a whole, just depending how far you take your mind within there.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not left, right, up or down, internal, external.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's within this.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is what I record in these tapes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that's absolutely it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, nobody could remember this.
[SPEAKER_00]: You remember it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I don't remember it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm just speaking from the same place.
[SPEAKER_01]: So we just come up the same way every time.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you were to ask me to repeat now what I said, I couldn't repeat in the same way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Funny, the thoughts that always... not always, but arise a lot, it's kind of a... what's the word you use?
[SPEAKER_00]: Trepidation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Kind of like, well, I don't know if I can even do this.
It's all so daunting.
Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then it's kind of like you recognize fairly quickly, like, well, okay, maybe, maybe not.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to still try.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's... that's probably the most important attitude to develop, or to abandon.
[SPEAKER_01]: Focus on this is to recognize that this is not out of my reach.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because most people will just dismiss it all.
[SPEAKER_00]: Too much.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just go drink or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, even if it's too much, that doesn't mean you have to... you should not do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You might get closer to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, next time won't be too much.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, effort won't go to waste.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, it's not too much.
[SPEAKER_01]: You were born... you were lucky enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: You had enough good merit to be born as a human.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you've done enough good in the past to have intact faculties.
[SPEAKER_01]: You've done enough good in the past to have intact intellect.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's absolutely no excuse there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're a reasonable human being with operating faculties and operating mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: That has time, relatively speaking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absolutely no other... That's such a perfect requirement.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you were a deva, you would be more unfortunate.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're not human, you'd be more unfortunate.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're lower than human.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you realize, actually, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no excuse.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, again, as I said, everybody can be mindful.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you don't have to worry in terms... you have to just, like, memorize that whole canon or... or understand every little angular point that Yanavera was talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those are just his ways.
[SPEAKER_01]: He would come out when we would... when he would be describing the same experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: The experience of the right view that other people might describe.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, they can say it differently, but it wouldn't mean different things.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means the same, they can just explain it differently, or not, not so detailed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because many, many, even in the suttas, they would have said, you know, there can be an arahant, but he has no gift of speech, no gift of explanation.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can still explain, but not to the vast group of people, to diversify his explanation, because he just doesn't have those capacities.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it doesn't mean that he does not have the meaning of the explanation.
[SPEAKER_01]: If he were, he wouldn't be an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, everybody can be mindful of the experience as a whole, and you know that's where you're supposed to look.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's where you start.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you're not actually trying to accomplish anything, in terms of understanding all of this, and figuring it all out.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you're trying to accomplish is become impermeable to suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's done on the basis of the mindfulness of the experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_01]: Four Noble Truths.
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing else.
[SPEAKER_01]: You understand that?
[SPEAKER_01]: You understood it all.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because everything is within that.
[SPEAKER_00]: As in discerning what is suffering origin in...
[SPEAKER_01]: Being free from.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just don't even worry about four.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just think about one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Completely free.
[SPEAKER_01]: Free directly and free peripherally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Means free from possibility to suffer as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes even I've found hard to identify.
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I currently, like,
[SPEAKER_00]: Suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, then you ask yourself, well, yeah, okay, maybe not now, because maybe now a neutral feeling is present.
[SPEAKER_00]: But at some point...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Am I completely free from any liability towards suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: And you can know that for sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's actually the criteria.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not whether you suffer right here, right now, but whether you can suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's all you have to do, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: Absolutely nothing else.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's kind of interesting that it went from talking about sense-plunge to something that kind of... Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And as you would guess, the Brahma is like, I don't get it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the Buddha gives in another verse.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's kind of similar.
[SPEAKER_00]: One who conceives, I am equal, I am better, I am worse.
[SPEAKER_00]: On account of that,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, at that point, it's kind of like it's less... he's getting less and less subtle with his verses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even still, it's a pretty subtle verse, and David doesn't get that one.
[SPEAKER_00]: And all of their questions, I mean, are in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: I have to be, if I can be better or worse, and whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Better or...
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm equal, I'm better, I'm worse.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means you're taking yourself to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: It means you are centered in that center I was talking about.
[SPEAKER_01]: As long as that's the case, there will be disputes, there will be upsets, there will be suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Finally, the first thing, the
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that not finding, it's because, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't even say they don't exist anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't, no, because then we apply to things that do exist.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's gone beyond.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can't be conceived.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like gone beyond the duality, so to say.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even that is a formal designation, and that can be misunderstood, if one is not mindful of how he has gone beyond.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's still a position.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, like, what Sāyantānī Sarā says, oh, the unbinding.
[SPEAKER_01]: The flame is not extinguished, it's unbound.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it hasn't ceased there, and now gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's kind of gone, sure, somewhere else, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Some undiscoverable location.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Inexpressible state that you just expressed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Really is a... designation really is a tangle, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's all there is, Rick.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all the tangles, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: True enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: Finally, I was saying, one should not do any evil in the world, not with a speech mind or body, having abandoned certain pleasures, mindful, clearly comprehending, one should not pursue the course that is painful and harmful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, it's just interesting how it kind of, like, went in kind of many different directions from that one thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, you know, why would the Buddha, like, I guess, say something if he, I would assume, knew the day that he wouldn't get it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, no, he couldn't get it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, no?
[SPEAKER_00]: Didn't he have the power, like, to discern people's minds?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, but it doesn't mean, like, really know, like, every turn it will take.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, he wouldn't... he would teach only to people who became irons.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not everybody came out to listen to him.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's a matter of choice for them as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he knew that they were... can possibly understand, which is why he kept trying.
[SPEAKER_01]: He said, sometimes I teach some people and I give them instruction clearly and everything, but they will do the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I'm displeased in a count of minutes, but that feeling does not overtake my mind, so I don't get upset.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, I waste my time.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has another sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: You've talked about some of them before, but I just had one particular question.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that sutta where Buddha talks about, like, one should treat foods like they're dear
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know where it was.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, I would do the basic, like, the simile makes sense, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: But just the idea of, like, nutriments.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, okay, the food makes sense, you need to nurture the body, otherwise it'll shrivel away into nothing.
But then the other
[SPEAKER_01]: So, these are nutriments, obviously, only when ignorance is present.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't think about, like, when commentaries describe contact, it's just coming together of three things.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can watch it on a screen.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it means that the sense of self is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the sense of self depends upon being contacted by things that are appropriate.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the verb is pusati.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah, being touched, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what is it they're nurturing?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, they're nurturing stuff to what?
[SPEAKER_01]: To the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: To the sense of self.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am the appropriation to all it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're not touched, it's not inappropriate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the whole thing depends on the fact that you're just being touched constantly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And whatever results in that, like, feeling, the perceptions, all... Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Under that kind of...
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: All nourished by that touch.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's kind of saying that
[SPEAKER_01]: To put it more simply, it's because you take things to be mine, your sense of self is maintained.
[SPEAKER_01]: You stop taking everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when I say take, I mean mentally own.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like not, as I said it before, not going to destroy all the possessions, because then, obviously, mental ownership will still remain.
[SPEAKER_01]: As we spoke before, you remain in regard to your senses.
[SPEAKER_01]: And since you haven't discerned what mental ownership as a phenomenon is, even in regard to the objects, you're not going to certainly discern it then in your senses when you when you thought that you free yourself from ownership by destroying the things you own.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to discern the mental ownership.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, your sense of self is not maintained.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in that way, those last two are a little different than edible food.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, they're subtler.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, basically, as long as there is a determination that's rooted in ignorance, there's going to be the whole... but it's all part of the results in suffering, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, ultimately, the ultimate determination and realization is consciousness.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as long as there is presence of things, as long as things are arising, there will be suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: We can say that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, all that means when ignorance is there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Once ignorance is dispelled in regard to nature of manifestation, nature of presence, nature of consciousness, then there's no problem anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because there's some similarities you mentioned.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah, if it leans, if it sits, yeah, you don't don't rest on anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: You use that in regards to contact.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like whatever your contact with has the potential to be devouring.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, no, every contact is devouring, because contact already means ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Touched.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can only be touched when you're ignorant, which means the fact that contact, even as a pleasant contact, is touching you, it's already devouring.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why sensual pleasures are actually painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Actually painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even like the most refined contact, like joy and jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, not necessarily, though.
[SPEAKER_01]: No?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, theoretically, supposedly, say, someone without a right view, but, yeah, you want to replace joy with jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: You want to use joy with jhāna to replace joy with sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, relatively speaking.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ultimately, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Again, if ignorance is there, which can be, even the one who has jhānas,
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, there's still going to be contact.
[SPEAKER_01]: From the ultimate fundamental point of view, you don't want contact at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: However, refining contact in regard to the wholesome states, as opposed to in regard to the unwholesome states, can make you and certainly enable you to see contact, natural contact, clearer and then free yourself from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why, along with jhānas, we need very little instruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Kutujana has jhānas.
[SPEAKER_01]: You've already done 90% of the mind development.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, now you just need to get together, get a few bits, pieces right, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you'll know how to look at the whole thing correctly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, there's there's two other similes for the other ones.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let's see... How, because should the nutrient mental volition be seen?
[SPEAKER_00]: Suppose there's a charcoal pit deep within man's height, filled with burning coals.
[SPEAKER_00]: Man will come along wanting to live, not wanting to die, desiring happiness in the worst of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then two strong men will grab him by both arms, drag him towards the charcoal pit.
[SPEAKER_00]: A man's volition would be to get far away.
[SPEAKER_00]: His longing would be to get far away.
[SPEAKER_00]: His wish would be to get far away from the charcoal pit.
[SPEAKER_00]: For what reason?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because he knows, I will fall into this charcoal pit, on account of that,
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't exactly understand the connection there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mental volition, I think that's cetanā.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is the nutriment sankhāra?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, cetanā is sankhāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sankhāra is just the fundamental nature of determination.
[SPEAKER_01]: But cetanā is already determination.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, basically your intentions.
[SPEAKER_01]: away from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the same simile you use how to avoid sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, putting your mind...
[SPEAKER_01]: In thrown into a chunkle, like burning amber, you get a burning amber, and your mind would be everywhere else except wanting to be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means the mind has to stop wanting you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because simply by wanting sensuality, you are still within the domain of sensuality, even if you're never engaging it for the rest of your life.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you're still feeling it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, one should... Not feed it.
[SPEAKER_01]: See it as the most dangerous thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Develop that intention to avoid it and overcome it.
[SPEAKER_01]: When it's there, develop intention that you are not going there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you're being taken there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, but no, you want to be everywhere else except there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's enough to not feed it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Provided you stop engaging in it by body and your senses beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, it's just hypocritical.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, you won't actually stand for anything that matters.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would be abstract.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Divorce from what's actually in there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Completely divorced.
[SPEAKER_00]: It does not apply to... That's why people can think of that, like the danger centrality, but then they go engage in anyway.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And people, you can be like monks of 40, 50 years of practicing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it was in the church, and then they saw and go and find a woman.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the mind has never left.
[SPEAKER_00]: Very scary.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I suppose, yeah, there's a possibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you think that one could fall into such a trap?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the trap is scary, sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the fact is that it's their own doing, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you spend 50 years not freeing yourself from it, well, you have nobody else to blame, except yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like that you were bound
[SPEAKER_01]: Simply by a chance, and you have absolutely nothing to do about it, you couldn't do anything about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you can.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just didn't know what, because you didn't make the effort to find out.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think a lot... you know the dasa dhamma sutta?
[SPEAKER_00]: Which one's that?
[SPEAKER_00]: The ten perceptions of the four.
[SPEAKER_00]: I always thought about the last one, that like, you know, you know, the perception...
The end of my life?
Yeah, that I won't be embarrassed.
[SPEAKER_00]: I just think, yeah, what if I'm like a... if I make it that part, 30-year monk, and, you know, people ask,
[SPEAKER_00]: What have you attained?
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, the last simile is regarding consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: How, because should the nutrient conscious be seen?
[SPEAKER_00]: Suppose they were to arrest a bandit, a criminal, and bring him before the king, saying, Sire, this man is a bandit, a criminal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Impose on him whatever punishment you wish.
[SPEAKER_00]: The king says to them, Go, men, in the morning, strike this man with a hundred spears.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the morning, they strike him with a hundred spears.
Then, at noon,
[SPEAKER_00]: King asks, how is that man still alive?
Then, you go with me and show him the hundred more spears and so on and so forth.
What do you think, Bhikkhu, is with that man being struck with 300 more spears?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's going back to the idea of, so long as there is consciousness appropriated, there's going to be the opportunity for pain, suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even the mere presence of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Presence hasn't been understood, means things have been appropriated.
[SPEAKER_01]: And once you start seeing that, that very root, basically, of the experience, as
[SPEAKER_01]: Being struck by spirit, it will develop full dispassion towards anything else that comes down the line through that appearance of the experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's also more than just simply, I think, seeing that, oh, life is generally... Oh, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have a right view for any of those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Most of that, most of the suttas we saw, bhikkhus, means all sotāpannas, at least.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, bhikkhu was already assumed.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, he's already a sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the ones that haven't, you hear about them, suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: The son of the fisherman, they're the other one.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right, the one with the wrong views.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, all of this you need the right view for.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, yeah, you can go and moan your whole life and think that life's horrible, but that's not enough for you, aren't you?
[SPEAKER_01]: You have the right view, and then develop dispassion.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is a view?
[SPEAKER_01]: View, basically... Like, I could say those things again.
[SPEAKER_00]: I could say views.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, I viewed.
[SPEAKER_00]: What was a view?
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you think a view is?
[SPEAKER_01]: Ask yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is a view?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do you want me to tell you or just ask me?
[SPEAKER_00]: Describe it.
[SPEAKER_01]: How would you describe it to yourself?
[SPEAKER_01]: Just any.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't worry about any standard definition.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just describe it whichever way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, there is... however experienced it might be.
It may...
I may understand, but I may not.
Whatever...
[SPEAKER_00]: My understanding of it is, whether it's wrong or right, be a view, but then the confusion comes of... you go beyond view at some point.
[SPEAKER_00]: How could that be?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, but what is a view?
[SPEAKER_01]: The nature of a view?
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter good or bad, right or wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: View.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is, what is, what is... How would you describe a view?
[SPEAKER_01]: How would I?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, how is it in the nature of a view?
[SPEAKER_01]: How would you define?
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you call it a direction?
[SPEAKER_01]: View of something?
[SPEAKER_01]: Point of view?
[SPEAKER_01]: Coming from something?
[SPEAKER_01]: Centered in something?
[SPEAKER_01]: Something is being viewed?
[SPEAKER_01]: How would you describe it?
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't mean in terms like I'm viewing the cup.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even that!
[SPEAKER_01]: Viewing the cup.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just view in general.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not talking about you understanding what I'm viewing right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just
[SPEAKER_01]: Read the word view.
[SPEAKER_01]: What does it mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: Any view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Looking with your eyes, view through the window.
[SPEAKER_01]: What does it mean?
[SPEAKER_01]: Seeing something.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there is already the direction implied.
[SPEAKER_01]: From here, you're seeing something there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And same goes for the mental view.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just the right view is the view that's not rooted in unwholesome, not rooted in assumption.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then, it's still a direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: The mind towards phenomena.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, well, we can say consciousness, but obviously then consciousness would stand for something, say, of the mind towards the phenomena.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because consciousness is out there with phenomena more than it's with your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the point is,
[SPEAKER_01]: You have the wrong view, obviously, a view that's not even aware of itself as a view, and then you get the right view, the view that looks at things as they are.
[SPEAKER_01]: It still looks at them as they are, but an arahant, done that so much, he doesn't even look at them as they are, because that's what they are.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you've got to be on the view.
[SPEAKER_01]: The view is not required.
[SPEAKER_01]: His look at things rightly, it's not required, because what he has is things rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: The view is like a tool.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, think about, like, when when I say, you know, you set up your mindfulness of your experience at home and then you apply a reflection correctly based on instruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: All of that implies already the direction of the view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you can be refining your efforts to the point where you just have the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, zero effort required.
[SPEAKER_01]: All you have to do is look.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because how you look is the right way to look.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you don't need... No effort, no secular explanations, no setup, no descriptions.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just look at it, and you look at it rightly, because that's how you train your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: You look at it rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Arahant can stop doing that as well, because he can't even conceive wrong anymore, whether he looks or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, he is going beyond view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Could we call it then, like, more in the verb, like, right viewing or wrong viewing?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The reason why they call it right view, as a noun, is just because you kind of talk about the nature of viewing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But there's absolutely no view without viewing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, literally, viewing, seeing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's effortless.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's very, very, like, zero effort required.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you have to have a view, it may or may not be corresponding to what is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that means that you don't have the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: But even the wrong view is kind of effortless.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just... you don't have to make any further effort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, you have to make loads of effort to undo the wrong view, but when you do so, what you have is the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's all that matters.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because then, he doesn't have to make any further effort except just keeping that view inside, not forgetting about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it possible for the children to even recognize their wrong views?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: When they do, they become so advanced.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, not until that point?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, maybe to a degree.
[SPEAKER_00]: That would be like a very coarse one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's not like putujana-vumbh, sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just like a putujana-asutava, who is completely uninstructed, then the one who is instructed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, already, if he keeps pursuing that instruction, he becomes like a dhamminusāri or sādhanusāri.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, he's not yet sotāpanna, but he's kind of already attained to the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: He already developed the criteria.
[SPEAKER_01]: And if he carries on, he will reach, become sotāpanna.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't even forget about sotāpanna, sakadāgāmī, whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Those are just the milestones that the Buddha singled out in response to, like, being constantly questioned, where people rebought after their practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he said, well, here are the guidelines you can infer yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: But before that, he just wasn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: He was just one who sees and one who doesn't see.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the one who sees, is he finished?
[SPEAKER_01]: No, not quite yet.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, is he free from sensuality?
[SPEAKER_01]: But he has the right view?
[SPEAKER_01]: He has the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes he doesn't even talk about sakadāgāmī.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes it's just three mouths, depending on who he sees as relevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: The point is, you have to keep trying to understand where the wrong view is.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how you get the right view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, you have to keep trying to understand where the right view is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can get closer to understanding what you're trying to understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: Still not quite understand, so you're still kind of a pratījana, but you're definitely closer to understanding than a pratījana who never made the effort to understand at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like a gradual shoving of the sea, as the sīla says.
[SPEAKER_01]: The practice is very gradual, there's no sudden drop.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so you can
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you do it from an internal point of view, then you'll be sānasambuddha.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or vajekabuddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, eh... yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to do that, because you have all the instructions you need.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was thinking about that a lot of the... you know, a lot of times, you know, the teachings in places will come out as a lot of stories.
Like, especially... a lot of... you know, a lot of commentary stories I've found.
Yeah.
I remember this one.
It came to my mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's called the one on Śrīla Pāṇṭhaka.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do you remember that one?
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe.
[SPEAKER_00]: The way it goes, like there's two brothers.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, yes, yes, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: A gothic reporter.
[SPEAKER_01]: I know there's something else, man.
[SPEAKER_00]: Go for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, that one's in the Majjhima Nikāi.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is the commentary.
[SPEAKER_00]: That there were two brothers, I think, Mahāpāntika and Chulapāntika.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think that was their names.
[SPEAKER_00]: Chulapāntika wasn't very mentally strong.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, they both ordained, but Chulapāntika couldn't, like, memorize any suttas or understand them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he was... his brother said, oh, you might as well just disrupt your two stupids.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, he was going to throw the serm that was his mind and came to him in a flash of light and said, you know, just take this cloth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Keep doing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, my goodness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Keep rubbing the cloth.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then it said, oh, he saw eventually how it got dirty.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, my goodness.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, that sounds very commentarial.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's these little stories that make it all just... Oh, there's a story.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a story of that king.
[SPEAKER_01]: We saw the mango tree being ripped apart, because people want to get the mangoes.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you say, here, you got it right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because here it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not worth the beauty and the sensuality, because you get destroyed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in his mind, abandoned.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it's not, um...
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not necessarily wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe, he did.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's wrong to say that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because then, people would think that's what enlightenment is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not the hard work you put in, and repetition.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's like a magical little divine blessings of a stupid idiot rubbing the cloth and becoming enlightened as a result of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's all you need to do now.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he certainly would have not got the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: He might have been rubbing the cloth for whatever reason.
[SPEAKER_00]: He also developed psychic powers.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wow.
[SPEAKER_01]: Amazing.
[SPEAKER_00]: The rest of the story goes that he made a thousand copies of himself and no one could figure out which one was the real one.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, as if that sounds somehow relevant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Commentaries like to mention these things, but say somebody really recognized the wearing down of things, and then applied the same extrapolated nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a very subtle mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a very refined mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's far from stupid.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the thing is, see, the commentary doesn't put the emphasis on that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Say there was a case of somebody without the cloth and got that and had the refined mind to apply that to himself, and that was enough, that application to make him another one.
[SPEAKER_01]: They don't dwell on that, because they themselves were putujanas, commentators.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: If they had the right view, they would know where the practice lies in.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, but they genuinely thought if you rub the cloth, you can become an arahant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, if you stared at clay pots, you can go to the earth casino.
[SPEAKER_01]: Hence, if you do this, you observe the soles of your feet, you will become proficient in whatever jhāna, I don't know what else.
[SPEAKER_01]: They can just see a full month's degree of... Just cloth rubbish.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: The whole meditation technique.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just rub the cloth.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, that's the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I was saying, there was a case of something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact that commentary put emphasis on the fact that, oh, there was a tree being destroyed and that's what King saw and he became enlightened as a result of seeing.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: If he became enlightened, like, for example, Bhāgavata became enlightened and the Buddha told him in seeing that he's on seeing, you know, because his mind was previously developed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, this little instruction, which is not on the same footing as rubbing the cloth, it's the actual instruction,
[SPEAKER_01]: Was enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: But commentary goes so far, and people like to believe that, especially today, whereby no instruction is even necessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just have to find that magical little thing to do, and enlightenment will happen just as a finger snap.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're enlightened forever, afterwards.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you go, oh, I had this experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: People would say that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you have the experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what 500 years are.
[SPEAKER_01]: I have loads of experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: We all have experiences.
[SPEAKER_01]: My grandmother had experiences.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everybody has experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's nothing special about any experience at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: When there's only one special experience, that's when you abandon all the experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's not the experience that you can just have.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the experience you can develop.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, if it's not given to you, you developed it, which means you can't be taken away from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You didn't come by chance.